Guide to the Wentworth Family papers, 1902-1926, undated MS2116
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Wentworth Family papers
1902-1926, undated
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Wentworth family
MS2116
4.5 Linear Feet
Collection contains biographical information on Hazel and John Wentworth, as well as personal papers, correspondence, publications and programs.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Historical or Biographical Note
The Wentworth Papers collection contains a rich genealogic history of both Hazel and John Wentworth, the couple who are its primary focus, and what appears to be a collection of Hazel's personal papers. Unfortunately the collection's donor record could not be found thus little information is known about the Wentworths except that contained within the collection. However by combining this information with Hazel Wentworth's obituary (Washington Post 11/12/98) and the information presented in The Washington Theatre Club collection, also held by George Washington University, enough is known to present a brief biographical sketch for Hazel Wentworth. Hazel H Wentworth was born to Sherman and Myrna Hupper in Melrose MA, circa 1906. She graduated from Smith College in 1930 and moved to Washington DC sometime in the late 1940s. During the 1950s, she taught learning-disabled children in the DC public schools and at the Kingsbury Center. In 1957 she founded the Washington Theatre Club in Georgetown with her husband John Wentworth. The Theatre Club focused on introducing new productions, playwrights and performers and also housed a drama school to provide training for all ages and interaction with professional performers and directors. (For additional information on the Theatre Club please see the Washington Theatre Club collection.) In 1981 Hazel moved to Maine but returned to the DC area in 1989. At some point she and John Wentworth had two daughters, Rebecca and Karen, but the couple was later divorced. Hazel died of cancer on November 12, 1998 at Iliff Nursing Home in Dunn Loring.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains biographical information on Hazel and John Wentworth, as well as personal papers, correspondence, publications and programs.
Collection Organization
Organized into four series: Hazel H. Wentworth genealogy, John B Wentworth genealogy, Hazel Wentworth, and Miscellaneous.
Washington (D.C.); Biography; Wentworth,, Hazel H.; Wentworth, John B.
- Hazel H. Wentworth geneology, undated; MS2116 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of family histories.
  - Hazel H Wentworth genealogy, undated (Box 1)
    General note
  - Nelson Hall and Rebecca Hall, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sherman Blake Hupper (1865-1949) and Myrna Estelle Hupper (1881-?), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sherman and Myrna Hupper - Massachusetts Properties, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sherman and Myrna Hupper - Maine Properties, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Myrna Hupper - Insurance Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- John B. Wentworth geneology, undated; MS2116 Series 2; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  Unfortunately the information provided in the series is less straightforward and conclusive as that in Hazel's. We have information for two distinct family lines however it is unclear what, if any, is the relation between the two lines and from which John B Wentworth comes. Therefore I will explain simple explain the known information about these two family lines. The first line originates with the Ackerman family. George Ackerman, who died in 1941, was married to Mattie E Ackerman. They had a daughter Marie Louise Ackerman, born in 1875 and a son named Henry. Marie married George Edmund Wentworth, born in 1866, in 1902. And Marie often corresponded with a niece named Gertrude. The other line begins with John "Long John" Wentworth (1815-1888.) John was the 16th mayor of Chicago. His nephew was Moses J Wentworth who married Lizzie Shaw Hunt Wentworth in 1891. Moses dies in 1922 and Lizzie in 1935. Lizzie's obituary states that she was outlived by a son, John Wentworth however it is completely unknown if this could be the John who married Hazel or simply another one of his relatives. This series consists of family histories.
  - John B Wentworth genealogy, undated (Box 1)
  - General Wentworth Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - George Ackerman (?-1941), undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Marriage Certificate of George Wentworth and Marie L Ackerman, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence between RMS Putnam and George Wentworth, 1919-1926 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Marie Louise Ackerman (1875-?) - Personal Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Marie Louise Ackerman - Business Transactions, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Hazel Wentworth geneology, undated; MS2116 Series 3; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2)
  This series includes what appears to be a collection of Hazel's personal papers including her correspondence and various articles, publications, playbills and programs which were apparently of interest to her, among other things. This series includes biographical sketch; Smith College; correspondence; Articles and publication on Washington Theatre Club; Alliance for Arts Education; Children's Theatre; General Theatre Articles and Publications.
  - Hazel Wentworth, undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketch, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Smith College, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Articles and publication on the Washington Theatre Club, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Alliance for Arts Education, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Children's Theatre, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Theatre Articles and Publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Hazel Wentworth, undated (Box 2)
  - Performing Arts in Maine, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Playbills and Programs of various productions, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Library for the arts, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Records, undated; MS2116 Series 4; 1.5 Linear feet (Box 2)
  This series includes documents, which could not be sufficiently identified for better classification.
  This series includes genealogical information reaching back to Hazel's grandparents. I will now provide a brief ancestral sketch complied from this information.
  Nelson Hall, Hazel's grandfather, was born in Belfast Maine and was a Corporal in the US Sharp Shooters. He was discharged from service in 1863 and returned home to his wife, Rebecca Hall. The couple resided in Meadford, Massachusetts and in 1899 they adopted Myrna Wiley, born in 1881. Myrna then married Sherman Blake Hupper, born in 1865. Sherman was an Ensign in the navy and was discharged from service in 1928. The couple resided in Massachusetts where they owned two properties: one in Wilmington and the other in Stoneham. They had a daughter and a son. Their daughter was Hazel. This series includes information on Katherine C Wiggin in the form of correspondence; miscellaneous documents; photographs; various coins; school notebook; free coupon book for The Sperry & Hutchinson Co; address book.
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Katherine C Wiggin, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Various Coins, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - School Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Free Coupon Book for The Sperry & Hutchinson Co., undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Address Book, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)